so the sutas speak of someone who has
attained the final goal as having laid
down the
burden I was wondering if you could
explain what this
means what is the
burden and how does one put it
down the burden is uh the burden of I
identification with things that make up your existence
with things that make up your existence
identification with
existence and by that I mean Aggregates
so identification with the components of
what make your world up your experience
up and that in Buddhist in in Buddhist
terminology is five
Aggregates so laying down the burden is
is removing the Assumption in regard to
those Aggregates Aggregates that that
they are what I
am because by you know by identifying
with the body by saying or viewing or or
viewing it as this is who I am what I am
well whatever the body goes to that is
your burden that is the burden you carry
the body because you're taking it
up as yours thus you will feel the
weight of it whatever wherever it goes
whatever happens to it so
Decay the the energy of
growth the the deple when it's
depleted the sickness the agitation the
fever the
itches that's all yours as well so you
might uh like to focus on the pleasant
parts of the body the pleasant
experiences but that's even all those
pleasant experiences are wrapped up
within the weight and burden of the body
as a whole which uh if you can see that
far outweighs the The Little Pleasures you
outweighs the The Little Pleasures you
have the actual having to eat and and
live and clean it and all that's that's
the big that's what the body is for you
not these little pleasures you get from
from it from The Taste a bit of
sugar and how does um so how does that
identification then come to
be how can one undo
that and so the way to uh free yourself
from that identification from the
burden is to actually see the burden
to have a p real in a real perspective
on the body as I just said what the body
really is because when you see the the
the the larger context of the body or
the the true nature of the
body the disgusting nature of it the
burdensomeness of it you will your mind
will turn away from it there won't be
this delighting in it and thus this
identification with it so what you're
saying then is that that
identification comes through and it's
maintained through delighting in the
body finding pleasure in the
body yeah but you only have that because
you don't see the body for what it is
you you you're just focusing on the the
small insignificant
Pleasures not the bigger picture of it
so if you were to stop focusing on small
Pleasures stop pursuing them stop acting
out of them
would that make identification with the
body diminish
yes likewise with other Aggregates and
particularly feeling you know you you don't see the
feeling you know you you don't see the
whatever you feel you're just
automatically that that's you you know
you that's what you feel like you're
identified with identified with it in
instantaneously and
but if you look at if you
just step back for a while and
not and try to gain a
perspective through the various means of
virtue and self and cental
straint try to investigate feelings you
know are you in control those feelings
do they come
randomly you know you can try to aim for
pleasure but doesn't really always work
out to the extent that you want it to
work out and even when it does it
doesn't stay as long as you
want and so if you're identified with
that and not even not
even if you're identified with feelings
you don't even see feelings actually and
whatever that wherever that feeling goes
so will you go your mind will change
accordingly so when it's up pleas
Pleasant you're up you're happier
everything's good R and then all of a
sudden it changes to pain that
pleasure's gone and you're extremely
depressed and that whole up and
down makes you even makes the situation
so much worse because it shows you it
feels like you're not in control of
yourself really that will breed anxiety
suffering so even when you have pleasure
even when you get the feeling that you
want at the back of your mind there's
always that sense and sensitivity to
I got to you know I can't keep this
pleasure it's going to be lost because
you know deep deep down that
it's you can't hold on to
it and that is a
burden feeling is actually a burden
identification with feeling is a
burden so in brief the laying down of
the burden is just that is
the realization of the true nature of the
realization of the true nature of the
body the true nature of feelings that it
those things are not yours they don't
belong to you they come and go as they
please they don't even know you or care
about you and your
wishes and by identifying with those
things you're going to suffer and the
Arun the noble disciple has the noble
disciple has laid down that burden of
authentification by being the nature of
it of those things and laying it down
then it doesn't matter what happens to
the body what experiences might occur there
body what experiences might occur there
is no burden because you're not there's
nobody taking it up there's no
identification anymore identifier ownership